3-42, Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

■ karim.ali@ualberta.ca | 🔏 karimali.ca | 🖸 karimhamdanali | 💆 @karim3ali

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages, compiler optimization, and software systems.

#### **Education**

Ph.D., Computer Science 2014

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Advisor: Ondřej Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

**MMath, Computer Science** 2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

**B.Sc., Computer Science** 2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- · Minor: Mathematics

## Professional Experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### **Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science**

University of Alberta, Canada

#### **Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science**

University of Alberta, Canada

#### **Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering**

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

- Host: Eric Bodden
- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- · Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

#### **Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group**

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs
- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

#### **Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group**

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods
- Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

## **Researcher, Department of Computer Science**

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems

Jul 2017-Present

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

Oct 2014-Jul 2016

2010-2014

2008-2009

ITWORX, EGYPT

• Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

## Awards and Honors \_\_\_\_\_

## **ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award**

2017

INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON SOFTWARE TESTING AND ANALYSIS

**Distinguished Artifact Award** 

2014

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON OBJECT-ORIENTED PROGRAMMING

**David R. Cheriton Scholarship**University of Waterloo, Canada

2012-2014 \$20,000

**Special Graduate Scholarship**University of Waterloo, Canada

**2012** \$2,500

**Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology CANADA** 

2012 \$5,000

Special Graduate Scholarship
University of Waterloo, Canada

2011

**Graduate Entrance Scholarship** 

\$1,000

University of Waterloo, Canada

2008 \$3,000

**B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors** 

2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

2007

**Best CS Group Graduation Project Award**The American University in Cairo, Egypt

TSE

Shell Endowed Scholarship

2003–2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

**Reviewer**, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering

30% off tuition

# Professional Service \_

Program Committee, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	ECOOP '18	
Program Committee, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	ISSTA '18	
Web Chair, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	ECOOP '18	
<b>Web Chair,</b> International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	ISSTA '18	
Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop	CASCON '17	
Program Committee, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering	CASCON '17	
<b>SPLASH-I Co-Chair,</b> ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity	SPLASH '17	
Program Committee, ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software Onward! '17		
Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems	ESSoS '17	
Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon	PLDI '17	
Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis	PLDI '17	
<b>Demonstration Track Co-Chair,</b> ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering	FSE '17	
Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction	CC '17	
Artifact Evaluation Committee, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	ISSTA '16	
Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks	ISSTA '16	
Artifact Evaluation Committee, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation	PLDI '15	
Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA	PLDI '15	
Artifact Evaluation Committee, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	ECOOP '15	
Reviewer, Science of Computer Programming	SCP	
Artifact Evaluation Committee, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	ECOOP '14	

# **Research Funding**

#### Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems

2017-2022

- · Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant
- With: Sole PI
- Amount: CAD\$125,000

## Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler

2017-2018

- IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship
- · With: Sole PI
- Amount: CAD\$30,000

## **Coarse-Grained Call Graph Analysis of Android Applications**

2017-2018

- Huawei Innovation Research Program (HIRP)
- · With: Sole PI
- Amount: USD\$46,200

## **Publications**

#### REFEREED JOURNAL ARTICLES

**Karim Ali**, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction Algorithms for Scala". *ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology*, 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015.

TOSEM '15

Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and **Karim Hamdan**. "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Management in Pervasive Systems". *International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security*, 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008.

IJCSNS '08

#### REFEREED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, **Karim Ali**, Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Christian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". *International Conference on Automated Software Engineering*, (to appear), 2017.

ASE '17 Tool Paper

OOPSLA '17

Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. " $IDE^{al}$ : Efficient and Precise Alias-aware Dataflow Analysis". *ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages and Applications*, (to appear), 2017.

FSP '17

Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, **Karim Ali**, and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". *International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers*, (to appear), 2017.

SCAM '17

Mona Nashaat, **Karim Ali**, and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". *IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation*, (to appear), 2017.

ISSTA '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-Time Static Analysis". *International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis*, pp. 307–317, 2017.

Distinguished Paper ICSE '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". *International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Volume*, pp. 39–42, 2017.

Tool Paper
ECOOP '16

Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 22:1–22:26, 2016.

Onward! '15

Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration of Cryptographic Software". *ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH*, pp. 1–13, 2015.

ECOOP '14

**Karim Ali**, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala Programs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 54–79, 2014.

Distinguished Artifact

**Karim Ali** and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 378–400, 2013.

ECOOP '13

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, pp. 688-712, 2012.

**ECOOP** '12

#### OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting DDoS flooding attacks". Global Information Infrastructure Symposium, 2009.

GIIS'09

Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". Global Information Infrastructure Symposium, 2009.

GIIS '09

## Selected Invited Talks

ware Implementation Technology, 2015.

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". University of Colorado Boulder, 2016.

Boulder '16

Boulder, CO, USA

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Rochester Institute of Technology, 2016.

RIT '16 Rochester, NY, USA

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Iowa State University,

ISU '16

2016. "Evaluating Call Graph Construction for JVM-hosted Language Implementations". IFIP Working Group 2.4 on SoftAmes, IA, USA IFIP '15

Boppard, Germany

"Averroes - Letting go of the library!" Samsung Research America, 2015.

SRA '15

Mountain View, CA, USA

"Whole-Program Analysis Without the Whole Program". McGill University, 2015.

Montreal, QC, Canada

McGill '15

## Students

Stefan Krüger

Lisa Nguyen

#### **CURRENT**

**Erick Ochoa** 2017–Present University of Alberta, Canada, (co-supervised with José Nelson Amaral)

2015-Present

**Johannes Späth** University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

Master's

2015-Present Ph.D.

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

2015-Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph D

#### ALUMNI

**Manuel Benz** 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

Ph.D. at University of Paderborn

Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs

Michael Appel TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY 2016

2015-2016

· Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

Software Engineer at Deutsche Telekom

· Ph.D. withdrawn

Stefan Triller

Teaching			
INSTRUCTO	DR .		
CMPUT 620 CMPUT 229 CMPUT 620 SAS	Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada Static Analysis Seminar, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Fall 2017 Winter 2017 Fall 2016 Winter 2015	
Co-Instru	CTOR		
APSA	Applied Static Analysis, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Spring 2016	
Substitu	TE LECTURER		
DECA CS 241	<b>Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems,</b> Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany <b>Foundations of Sequential Programs,</b> University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2014 Spring 2013	
GRADUATE	TEACHING ASSISTANT		
CS 241 CS 444/644 CS 446/646 CS 456/656 CS 125 CS 448	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2011–2013 2011–2013 Spring 2011 2008–2010 Winter 2008 Fall 2007	
Undergra	aduate Teaching Assistant		
CS 448 CS 330 CS 106	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt Computer Architecture, The American University in Cairo, Egypt Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007 2005–2006 2004–2005	
Volunte	er Work		
Graduate St Tour Guide President, Ushers Con	ot Technical Mentor, Strathcona High School, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada tudent Ambassador, University of Waterloo, Canada Computer Science Open House, University of Waterloo, Canada Egyptian Students Association, University of Waterloo, Canada Imittee Leader, Honors Assembly, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2016–2018 Fall 2013 Winter 2012 2010–2011 Spring 2007	

Academic Committee Head, ACM Chapter, The American University in Cairo, Egypt

Spring 2007